Women in Argentina, VII, 1993-2005: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library
Women in Argentina, VII
1993-2005
HQ1532 W654 1993
LAE001
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
1 linear feet 2 boxes 2 microfilm reels
Princeton University. Library.
This collection comprises a diversity of pamphlets, flyers, posters, newspapers, and other documents produced by political parties, women's organizations and movements, political and cultural organizations, city and state governments, as well as other publishers from Argentina.
The Princeton University Library has developed numerous collections of Latin American ephemera that are unique in their depth and scope. Privileging the popular voices of the region, the collections document numerous political and social movements, and a wide variety of key socioeconomic and cultural developments. Some particularly well-documented topics are grassroots organizing, human rights, electoral politics, indigenous issues, women and gender issues, youth, the environment, health, education, and religion. Types of primary materials collected include pamphlets, non-commercially produced and distributed serials, flyers, posters, working papers, government publications, and other non-traditional formats. Most of the documentation in the collections was produced after the mid 1960s by Latin American nongovernmental organizations of all types, interest groups, political parties, research institutes, and government agencies.
The intensive collecting of ephemera was initiated by Barbara Hadley Stein, the University’s first Bibliographer for Latin America, Spain and Portugal (1966-1977). She sought to document some of the major political developments of the period, including the rise to power of military dictatorships, coup d’états, the institutionalization of the Cuban Revolution, and the popular responses to those developments. Her successor, Peter T. Johnson (1977-2003), expanded the geographic and thematic scope of the collections and systematized the process of organizing, cataloging, and preserving them. Intensive collecting in this area continues to this date.
Over the years, materials have been grouped and organized by country or region, and by topic or subject area. Once collections are fully organized, they are cataloged and microfilmed. A complete list of collections appears in the Guide to the Princeton University Latin American Microfilm Collection (Wilmington, DE: Scholarly Resources, 1993) and subsequent supplements. Many of the collections’ finding aids are available online. Original print materials have been preserved in many cases.
This collection comprises a diversity of pamphlets, flyers, posters, newspapers, and other documents produced by political parties, women's organizations and movements, political and cultural organizations, city and state governments, as well as other publishers from Argentina. All materials reflect and relate to the situation and political involvement of Argentine women from the early 1990s onward, with an emphasis on the years and the annual encuentros de mujeres between 2000 and 2006. This collection is organized by publisher. In most sections, materials are then grouped alphabetically by title; the briefest pamphlets and flyers, usually two pages or less, are left untitled and grouped together.
The Latin American ephemera collections are open for research use.
Originals are stored offsite at the ReCAP facility. Microfilm surrogates can be consulted in Microforms Service, Firestone Library ( http://firestone.princeton.edu/microforms/).
Please consult with the Department of Rare Books and Special Collections about having the collection recalled to the Department for your use. This process normally requires 48-72 hours notice.
MICROFILM 12064
MICROFILM 7812 (Master printing copy. Available for reproduction only.)
Additional material related to the subjects addressed in this collection can be found in the collections listed below. For a complete list of Latin American ephemera collections, consult the Guide to the Princeton University Latin American Microfilm Collections (call number: Z1610 .G842 1993) and subsequent supplements.
Socioeconomic crisis and political participation in Argentina, I, 1995-2005
Women in Argentina, I: pamphlets, [1978-1985]
Women in Argentina, II: pamphlets, 1983-1988
Women in Argentina, III: pamphlets, 1984-1989
Women in Argentina, IV: pamphlets, 1986-1991
Women in Argentina, V: pamphlets, 1982-1998
Women in Argentina, VI, 1989-2001
Family violence -- Argentina.; Reproductive health -- Argentina.; Women -- Argentina.; Women -- Argentina -- Political activity.; Women -- Argentina -- Social conditions.; Women -- Crimes against -- Argentina.; Women -- Employment -- Argentina.; Women -- Health and hygiene -- Argentina.; Women's rights -- Argentina.; Women in politics -- Argentina.; Women labor union members -- Argentina.; Latin American studies
- Agrupación Pan y Rosas (s.l.), 2004-2005; portion of 1 box
  - Manifiesto Pan y Rosas, 2004; 24p (Box 001)
  - Pan y Rosas, 2004 August; portion of 1 box
    - Boletín No. 2, 2004 August; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
  - Pan y Rosas, 2004 March 8-2005; portion of 1 box
    - 2004 March 8, portion of 1 box (Box 001)
    - circa 2005, portion of 1 box (Box 001)
  - 2 flyers, circa 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
  - 1 pamphlet, 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Agrupación Víctor Choque de ATE (Asociación de Trabajadores del Estado) (Buenos Aires), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - El boletín de la VÍctor Choque, 2005 October; portion of 1 box
    - Año I, Número Especial, 2005 October; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
  - 1 flyer, 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Asociación de Especialistas Universitarias en Estudios de la Mujer (ADEUEM) (Buenos Aires), 2002; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, 2002; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Asociación de Mujeres Bonarenses (A.M.Bo.) (Buenos Aires), 1998; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, 1998; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Asociación de Trabajo y Estudio sobre la Mujer (ATEM) (s.l.), 2004; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Autoconvocatoria NO AL ALCA (Buenos Aires), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Bloque Obrero y Popular (s.l.), 2004; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Campaña Nacional por el Derecho al Aborto Legal, Seguro y Gratuito (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 2 flyers, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- La Casa del Encuentro (Buenos Aires), 2004 October-2005 November; portion of 1 box
  - Encontradas: revista lésbico feminista para todas las mujeres, 2004 October-2005 November; portion of 1 box
    - Edición Mensual, Año 1, 2004 October; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
    - Edición Bimestral, 2005 October-November; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
  - 1 flyer, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Católicas por el Derecho a Decidir (CDD) (Buenos Aires), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
  - 1 pamphlet, 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Central de los Trabajadores Argentinos (CTA) (Mendoza), 2004; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
  - 1 pamphlet, circa 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Centro de Comunicación Popular y Asesoramiento Legal (CECOPAL) (Córdoba), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - Economía Solidaria, 2000s; 14p (Box 001)
    (Cartillas en gestión de microemprendimientos en la economía solidaria 1)
- Centro de Encuentros Cultura y Mujer (CECYM) (Buenos Aires), 2002; portion of 1 box
  - Mujeres víctimas de violencia sexual: proteger, recuperar, reparar. Silvia Chejter y Beatriz Ruffa, 2002; 42p (Box 001)
- Centro de Estudios de Población (CENEP) (Buenos Aires), 1989; portion of 1 box
  - Trabajo, carrera y género en el mundo de la salud. Rosa N. Geldstein y Catalina H. Wainerman, 1989; 62p (Box 001)
    (Cuaderno del CENEP; No. 42)
- Centro de Estudios Políticos y Sociales Sobre Género (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Centro Interdisciplinario de Estudios Sociales Contemporáneos (CIESC) (Buenos Aires), 1989; portion of 1 box
  - Piedras en los bolsillos: miedo, violación, culpa. Inés Hercovich, 1989; 9p (Box 001)
- Colectivo Feminista "Viva la Pepa" (s.l.), 2003-2004; portion of 1 box
  - 3 flyers, 2003-2004; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Comisión de Género IMFC (Instituto Movilizador de Fondos Cooperativos) (Buenos Aires), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - 2 pamphlets, circa 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Comisión de Mujeres de la Alianza Social Continental (Mar del Plata), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Consejo Nacional de la Mujer (Buenos Aires), 1985-2003; portion of 1 box
  - Convención interamericana para prevenir, sancionar y erradicar la violencia contra la mujer (Ley 24.632, "Convención de Belém do Pará"), 2000; 21p (Box 001)
    (Serie La violencia contra la mujer)
  - Convención sobre la eliminación de todas las formas de discriminación contra la mujer (Ley 23.179), 1985; 16p (Box 001)
  - Mujer, equidad y trabajo: cuaderno de práctica, 2003; 64p (Box 001)
  - Mujer, equidad y trabajo: manual para facilitadoras y facilitadores, 2003; 167p (Box 001)
  - El trabajo en los talleres, 1999; 59p (Box 001)
    (Serie La violencia contra las mujeres en el ámbito de las relaciones familiares)
  - El trabajo en los talleres. ( 2002, 2 a edición revisada), 59p (Box 001)
- Consorcio Nacional de Derechos Reproductivos y Sexuales (CONDERS) (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Corriente Clasista y Combativa (CCC) (Buenos Aires), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - Alegatos del juicio: libertad a Romina Tejeríana, 2000s; 15p (Box 001)
- Corriente Praxis (Buenos Aires), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - XX Encuentro Nacional de Mujeres, 2005; 13p (Box 001)
- Debocaenboca (s.l.), 2004; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
  - 3 pamphlets, circa 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Ediciones Hoy (Buenos Aires), 2005 October 5; portion of 1 box
  - Hoy: seminario del comunismo revolucionario de Argentina, 2005 October 5; portion of 1 box
    - No. 1085, 2005 October 5; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Ediciones Se.A.P. (Servicio a la Acción Popular) (Córdoba), 1993-1996; portion of 1 box
  - Habitemos nuestro cuerpo. ( 1996, 2 a edición), 22p (Box 001)
  - El poder que queremos, 1993; 14p (Box 001)
- Editorial Agora (Buenos Aires), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - Mujeres: 20 encuentros. Pilar Sánchez, 2005; 42p (Box 001)
    (Cuadernos de Editorial Agora 10)
- El Espejo (Buenos Aires), 2005 October 4; portion of 1 box
  - El espejo de Argentina y el mundo, dates not examined; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
  - Año XI, No. 156 Extra, 2005 October 4; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Federación Universitaria Marplatense (FUM) / Federación Universitaria Argentina (FUA) (s.l.), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Feministas Autorganizadas (FEAS) (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Foro de Mujeres en Accion (Fo.Mu.A) (Neuquén), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - Agendita Solidaria, 2004 June; portion of 1 box
    - Edición Número 2, 2004 June; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
  - 1 pamphlet, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Frente Obrero Socialista (FOS) (Buenos Aires), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Fundación Agenda de las Mujeres (s.l.), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Fundación Género y Sociedad (s.l.), 2003 January; portion of 1 box
  - Pan para hoy: hambre para nadie, 2003 January; portion of 1 box
    - No.2, 2003 January; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Fundación para Estudio e Investigación de la Mujer (FEIM) (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
  - 3 pamphlets, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Fundación Poder Ciudadano (Buenos Aires), 1997; portion of 1 box
  - Herramientas de acción ciudadana para la defensa de los derechos de la mujer. Programa de participación y fiscalización ciudadana. Haydeé Birgin, 1997; 70p (Box 001)
- Fundación Propuesta (Buenos Aires), 2004 August; portion of 1 box
  - Fundación Propuesta: un espacio para la mujer frente a la discriminación y la violencia, 2004 August; portion of 1 box
    - Año 7, No.7, 2004 August; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Fundación TIDO (Trabajo, Investigación, Desarrollo y Organización de la Mujer) (Buenos Aires), 1999; portion of 1 box
  - Estrategias para microemprendedores/as. Juan José Greco, undated; 12p (Box 001)
    (Cuadernillos para Emprendedores/as; No. 4)
  - La globalización y inserción de las ONG's en este modelo. Miguel Cipriano, 1999; 18p (Box 001)
    (Cuadernillos para Emprendedores/as; No. 1)
  - Liderazgo femenino. Susana Gamba, undated; 26p (Box 001)
    (Cuadernillos para Emprendedores/as; No. 3)
  - Metodologías participativas y asociatividad. Cristina Jurnet, undated; 14p (Box 001)
    (Cuadernillos para Emprendedores/as; No. 2)
  - Planificación estratégica. Patricia Adriana Pinacho, undated; 16p (Box 001)
    (Cuadernillos para Emprendedores/as; No. 5)
  - Reinventar trabajos, crear igualdad: hacia la autonomía económica de las mujeres, undated; 47p (Box 001)
- Gobierno de la Ciudad de Buenos Aires (gobBsAs) (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - Guía bibliográfica: violencia contra la mujer, violencia doméstica, violencia sexual, maltrato infantil, undated; 21p (Box 001)
  - 5 pamphlets, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Grupo Estrategias por el Derecho al Aborto (Buenos Aires), 2003; portion of 1 box
  - Primer encuentro nacional por el derecho al aborto legal, seguro y gratuito, 2003; 38p (Box 001)
- Grupo Estudios Lésbicos (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 001)
- Huelga Mundial de Mujeres (HMM) (Santa Fe), 2002 July-2003 September; portion of 1 box
  - Huelga mundial de mujeres, 2002 July-2003 September; portion of 1 box
    - 2002 July, portion of 1 box (Box 002)
    - No. 2, 2003 September; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Instituto Social y Político de la Mujer (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 7 flyers, 6 pamphlets in a folder, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Juventud Comunista Revolucionario (Buenos Aires), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - Chispa: revista de la Juventud Comunista Revolucionaria, 2005 October; portion of 1 box
    - 2005 October, portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 1 flyer, circa 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 1 pamphlet, 2005; 1 item
- Marabunta Izquierda Revolucionaria (M-IR) (s.l.), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Mesa Feminista de Socialismo Libertario, 2005 October; portion of 1 box
  - XX Encuentro Nacional de Mujeres en Mar del Plata, 2005 October; portion of 1 box
    - No. 0, 2005 October; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Ministerio de Desarrollo Social y Salud, Gobierno de Mendoza (Mendoza), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Movimiento de Mujeres Córdoba (Córdoba), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 1 CD cover undated (photocopy), portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 3 pamphlets, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Movimiento de Mujeres Evita / Ministerio de Salud y Ambiente de la Nación (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Movimiento Socialista de los Trabajadores (MST), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 1 pamphlet, 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Movimiento Solidario por los Derechos de las Mujeres "Marie Langer" (Buenos Aires), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - 3 flyers, 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Mujeres al Oeste (Morón), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Mujeres de Convergencia Socialista (s.l.), 2004-2005; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 1 pamphlet, 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Mujeres de Empresa (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Mujeres de la Intersindical Clasista (Mar del Plata), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Mujeres de Socialismo Libertario (s.l.), 2003; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, 2003; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Mujeres del Movimiento Socialista de los Trabajadores (MST) (Mendoza), 2004; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Mujeres en Encuentro Amplio (Buenos Aires), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, circa 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Mujeres en Resistencia (s.l.), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - De la feminización de la pobreza a la feminización de la resistencia: feminismo de la solidaridad. María Elena Zavattiero y Diana Inés Rozas, undated; 6p (Box 002)
    (photocopy)
  - 1 flyer, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Mujeres Feministas Autoconvocadas (Mendoza), 2004; portion of 1 box
  - 4 flyers, circa 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Mujeres Libres (Buenos Aires), 2001-2002; portion of 1 box
  - 7 flyers, circa 2001-2002; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 3 pamphlets, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Organización del XIV Encuentro Nacional de Mujeres, 1999; portion of 1 box
  - Mujeres en el encuentro, circa 1999; 4p (Box 002)
- Organización del XIX Encuentro Nacional de Mujeres, 2004; portion of 1 box
  - 2 flyers 2004 in a folder, portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Organización Socialista Libertaria (OSL) (Buenos Aires), 2005 October; portion of 1 box
  - En la calle: órgano de difusión del anarquismo organizado, 2005 October; portion of 1 box
    - Edición Especial (XX Encuentro Nacional de Mujeres), 2005 October; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Partido Comunista Revolucionario (PCR) (Buenos Aires), 2004-2005; portion of 1 box
  - La liberación de la mujer. Comisión de Mujeres, 2005; 25p (Box 002)
  - 1 flyer, circa 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 1 pamphlet, 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Partido de Trabajadores Socialistas (PTS) (Mendoza), 2004; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, circa 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Partido Obrero (PO) (s.l.), 2004; portion of 1 box
  - 2 flyers, circa 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 1 pamphlet, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Partido Socialista (Buenos Aires), 2005; portion of 1 box
  - 2 flyers, circa 2005; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Plataforma del Movimiento Argentino de Mujeres y de Derechos Humanos por la Ratificación del Protocolo Facultativo de la Convención Sobre la Eliminación de Todas las Formas del Discriminación Contra la Mujer (CEDAW) (s.l.), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - 1 sticker, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 3 flyers, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 2 pamphlets, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 1 poster, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Red de Mendocinos por la Vida (Mendoza), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Red de Mujeres Solidarias (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 3 flyers, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
  - 3 pamphlets, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Red Informativa de Mujeres de Argentina (RIMA) (Santa Fe), 2000-2009; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, 2000s; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Sindicato de Amas de Casa (Santa Fe), 2004; portion of 1 box
  - 2 flyers, 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Unión de la Mujeres de la Argentina (UMA) (Buenos Aires), 2004; portion of 1 box
  - 1 pamphlet, 2004; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Unión del Personal Civil de la Nacion (UPCN) (Buenos Aires), dates not examined; portion of 1 box
  - 1 flyer, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)
- Unknown publishers, 2004; portion of 1 box
  - Mendoza, la provincia con más muertes por abortos ilegales, 2004; 1p (Box 002)
    (photocopied newspaper article from Los Andes, September 23, 2004)
  - Mujer y medios de comunicación. Nieves María Ámela, undated; 4p (Box 002)
  - 2 flyers, undated; portion of 1 box (Box 002)